<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>land cover mapping | Jose Don De Alban</title>
    <link>/tags/land-cover-mapping/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tags/land-cover-mapping/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>land cover mapping</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2020 Jose Don De Alban</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/don_baybayin.png</url>
      <title>land cover mapping</title>
      <link>/tags/land-cover-mapping/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>ALOS Kyoto &amp; Carbon Initiative Phase 4.</title>
      <link>/project/02_alos-kc-phase4/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/02_alos-kc-phase4/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UTILISING L-BAND SAR DATA FOR NATURAL RESOURCE MANAGEMENT IN THE PHILIPPINES (2014–2019).&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For ALOS K&amp;amp;C Phase 4, we intend to utilise JAXA ’s earth observation products, particularly ALOS/PALSAR-2, ALOS/PALSAR, and JERS-1 SAR data, to demonstrate the utility and viability of L-band SAR for natural resources management applications in the Philippines. We propose to utilise the data for the three thematic applications as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Land cover mapping and change detection.&lt;/strong&gt; We intend to assess the ability of spaceborne L-band SAR systems to support the generation of national baseline land cover and forest cover and change maps using a multi-level, hierarchical, land cover classification system.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;REDD+ and forest management.&lt;/strong&gt; Among the key activities to assess the potential of REDD+ initiatives is the credible baseline mapping of forest area changes, and estimation of forest biomass and carbon stocks, for which we intend to use JAXA’s L-band SAR datasets. Monitoring of forest area changes is also useful tool in order to assess the success of the forest protection and conservation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mangrove forest mapping and change monitoring.&lt;/strong&gt; We intend to utilise JAXA’s L-band SAR datasets to map the country’s mangrove cover extent and detect changes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similar to Phase 3, the ALOS K&amp;amp;C Philippines team is composed of representatives from Fauna &amp;amp; Flora International, Deutsche Gesellschaft für Internationale Zusammenarbeit GmbH, and the Department of Geodetic Engineering of the University of the Philippines. Other collaborators include staff of the National Mapping and Resource Information Authority and the Forest Management Bureau of the Department of Environment and Natural Resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Acknowledgements.&lt;/em&gt; The ALOS K&amp;amp;C Philippines team acknowledges the following organisations/projects for their support in the implementation of the project: (1) the &lt;em&gt;Biodiversity and Watersheds Improved for Stronger Economy and Ecosystem Resilience (B+WISER) Program&lt;/em&gt; funded by the United States Agency for International Development; (2) the &lt;em&gt;Preparation of a National REDD+ Mechanism for Greenhouse Gas Reduction&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Conservation of Biodiversity in the Philippines (National REDD+ System) Project&lt;/em&gt;, and the Forest and Climate Protection Phase II (ForClim II) Project, both funded by the International Climate Initiative of the German Federal Ministry for the Environment, Nature Conservation, Building and Nuclear Safety; and (3) the &lt;em&gt;Developing Capacities for Mapping and Monitoring of Philippine Mangroves using Synthetic Aperture Radar Data Project&lt;/em&gt; funded by the Philippine Tropical Forest Conservation Foundation. These projects are all implemented in partnership with the Department of Environment and Natural Resources.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
