<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Jose Don De Alban</title>
    <link>/authors/admin/</link>
      <atom:link href="/authors/admin/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Jose Don De Alban</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2020 Jose Don De Alban</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 03 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/icon.png</url>
      <title>Jose Don De Alban</title>
      <link>/authors/admin/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Improved estimates of mangrove cover and change reveal catastrophic deforestation in Myanmar</title>
      <link>/publication/2020-environ-res-lett/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/2020-environ-res-lett/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;medium-donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.1088/1748-9326/ab666d&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rebuilding my new website with Hugo, R blogdown, GitHub, and Netlify.</title>
      <link>/post/2020/02-02-building-my-new-website-with-hugo-blogdown-netlify/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Feb 2020 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2020/02-02-building-my-new-website-with-hugo-blogdown-netlify/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have been rebuilding my personal website using a static site generator, first, because I wanted a cleaner and streamlined site with an easy upkeep, plus I was motivated to learn the new tools, and more importantly, to move away from hosting on Wordpress due to the really annoying ads. The process was on and off, and although I found tips online that you can indeed complete it in a day or less, I only found time to on it very intermittently, mostly while in transit at airport terminals and during flights and over weekends, which was why it took about three months to deploy the site—and only last night, finally! The website is still incomplete and still under reconstruction, with most of my old blog posts and pages from my old 14n121e website to be slowly incorporated in my new website slowly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below, I have put together some guidance on how I built my new website, which you may find helpful in case you were wondering how you could go about building one for yourself too. I tried to put together the major steps with as much detail as I can recall, albeit I may have missed minor ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prerequisites&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After some prior searching online, I settled on using Hugo, R blogdown, GitHub, and Netlify as the combination of tools/resources I would employ for setting up and rebuilding my website. Note that I did not mind reconstructing the site manually (e.g., migrating contents such as blog post one by one) because it was not alot and also so I could understand the inner workings, hence I did not pursue (semi-)automated ways that existed for migrating content from Wordpress to the new site. To get started, I ensured the following online accounts were set up and the software tools were installed in my Mac OSX machine:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://git-scm.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Git&lt;/a&gt; and a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; account as the version control system for tracking the changes in a dedicated repository containing the website contents;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;R&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://rstudio.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;RStudio&lt;/a&gt;, the premier IDE for R, plus the &lt;a href=&#34;https://bookdown.org/yihui/blogdown/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;blogdown&lt;/a&gt; R package developed by &lt;a href=&#34;https://yihui.org/en/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Yihue Xie&lt;/a&gt;;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Then, &lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt;, an open-source static site generator for building websites, plus the &lt;a href=&#34;https://themes.gohugo.io/academic/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Academic&lt;/a&gt; Hugo theme by &lt;a href=&#34;https://georgecushen.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;George Cushen&lt;/a&gt;, of which was my personal choice as the theme for creating a simple and customisable website using the &lt;a href=&#34;https://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Markdown&lt;/a&gt; markup language (and it is apt for academics/scientists/researchers);&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition, I used some advanced features including &lt;a href=&#34;https://disqus.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Disqus&lt;/a&gt; to enable comments and discussions, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://marketingplatform.google.com/about/analytics/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Google Analytics&lt;/a&gt; to understand my website traffic; and&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finally, a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.netlify.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Netlify&lt;/a&gt; account to enable a fast and continuous deployment of the website, once the GitHub repository was connected and the build settings were added.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For most of the above, I already had prexisting registered accounts and had installed the tools, except for Netlify (so I had to sign up for a new account) and R blogdown and Hugo (both of which I had to newly install).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Creating a repository on Github&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Installing blogdown, Hugo and the Academic theme&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a final note, I have to say that the initial setup required some effort and time to learn a few new tools—and troubleshoot as required—but in the end, I was satisfied with the process and the outcome, and also from knowing that from here on the upkeep required to maintain my online presence would be minimal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used several resources online including&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;instructions of how to use Hugo, blogdown, and Netlify&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;helpful and easy-to-follow instructions form
Yihue Xie for blogdown
George Cushen for the Academic theme for Hugo&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;plus blog posts by XXX&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Katie Scanton&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Erika Fille Legara
Zhi Yang&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I referred to their posts, and sometimes even the GitHub-hosted repositories hosting their sites, as well as finding many bits of inspiration from the bespoke designs of their own websites&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;was really helpful&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Special thanks to Lloyd Zapanta for developing a true type font for the Baybayin script, which is the indigenous alphabet writing script of pre-colonial Philippines. He designed several true type fonts of the Baybayin script, of which I particularly used Baybayin Sisil rendition for creating my website logo, which is essentially my name written with Baybayin characters.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gold, farms, and forests—enforcement and alternative livelihoods are unlikely to disincentivize informal gold mining</title>
      <link>/publication/2020-conserv-sci-practice/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/2020-conserv-sci-practice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;medium-donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.1111/csp2.142&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Repos on GitHub.</title>
      <link>/post/2019/08-11-repos-on-github/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Aug 2019 20:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2019/08-11-repos-on-github/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have been sharing the coding materials and resources related to my research on my &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/dondealban&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;GitHub page&lt;/a&gt; but I have not had the chance to blog about these here at all, even briefly. And so, let me make this short introduction on my activities on GitHub, which does seem to show (and share) more of my research activity than in this blog. It&amp;rsquo;s just been about time too that I updated the &amp;lsquo;mugshot&amp;rsquo; on my GitHub page, which used to show an old (younger) photo of me, and now, more appropriately, shows a recent photo of me taken during the wedding of a dear colleague. Anyway&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./image_01.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, the repositories that accompany some of my published papers, either those I have led or had the great opportunity to co-author. I put together these materials to supplement the published papers, thereby creating a backup of the materials used and developed through the study such as data, results, scripts, and figures. By doing this, I was aiming to encourage not just other scientists and researchers but also my future self to do better science by fostering research reproducibility and transparency. It also improves the overall impact of my own research. Some of these repositories include materials for my &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/dondealban/ms-remote-sens-2018&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;2018 Remote Sensing&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/dondealban/ms-sustainability-2019&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;2019 Sustainability&lt;/a&gt; papers, as well as a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/dondealban/ms-conserv-biol-2017&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;2017 Conservation Biology&lt;/a&gt; paper, all of which were done together with my lab members and principal investigator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./image_02.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, I&amp;rsquo;ve created some repositories over the last couple of years for a lecture I gave at the ISPRS Student Consortium Summer School and Hackathon in 2018 where I shared about my land change research and ran a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/dondealban/isprs-sc-summer-school&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;crash course on Google Earth Engine&lt;/a&gt;, and a short &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/dondealban/tutorial-qgis-maxent&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;tutorial on species distribution modeling using MaxEnt and R&lt;/a&gt; that I did for my labmates during a lab retreat in 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I&amp;rsquo;ve also developed a couple of long how-to guides or tutorials while I was starting to learn some R packages in pursuit of my research ideas. There was one on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/dondealban/learning-stm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;stm package&lt;/a&gt; on structural topic modeling for text data mining and automated content analysis; and the other on the &lt;a href=&#34;(https://github.com/dondealban/learning-intensity-analysis)&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;intensity analysis package&lt;/a&gt;, which has been a key component of my research on land use/cover change analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quite frankly, I am stoked to see that users on GitHub have found these repositories (and some others I have not mentioned) useful as indicated by the number of stars or forks (take the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/dondealban/learning-stm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;learning-stm&lt;/a&gt; repo, for example).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please do watch my GitHub space for more updates on my research activities. If you find the materials and resources in any way helfpful, please &amp;lsquo;star&amp;rsquo; the repository page on GitHub, or cite the papers or accompanying repositories if you used them for your research. In case you want to contribute to the content in any of the repositories, please feel free to fork the repo and submit your pull request.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./image_03.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./image_04.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./image_05.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some impressions during the NASA SARI LCLUC science meeting.</title>
      <link>/post/2019/07-25-some-impressions-nasa-sari-lcluc-science-meeting/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jul 2019 22:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2019/07-25-some-impressions-nasa-sari-lcluc-science-meeting/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I had the opportunity to present a poster at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://lcluc.umd.edu/meetings/sari-searrin-meeting-and-training-malaysia-2019&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;international science meeting&lt;/a&gt; of the land cover / land use change (LCLUC) programme of NASA&amp;rsquo;s South/Southeast Asia Regional Initiative, held in Johor Bahru, Malaysia from 22nd to 24th of July 2019. My poster presentation was about our study on investigating land-cover regime shifts by integrating complementary analytical frameworks in the Tanintharyi Region, southern Myanmar, which was published earlier this year in a special issue of Sustainability journal (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/4/1139/htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;full paper here&lt;/a&gt;). I have not done a poster presentation in a very long while&amp;mdash;my last one was back in 2004, if my memory serves me right&amp;mdash;and so this time around it was an immensely gratifying experience, particularly seeing how other scientists were genuinely interested in what we found, how they thought of using the approaches and results of our study to build on their own work, as well as providing constructive feedback. Actually, I even won, to my utmost surprise, the 3rd best poster award out of about 50 posters presented during the meeting!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./image_01.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am starting to think I prefer doing poster presentations now better than oral presentations simply because the posters get to stay on display for the duration of the meeting and the people who engage and interact with you during poster sessions, in my opinion, are those who are really interested in your work or have the same research interests as you. In oral presentations, of which I&amp;rsquo;ve done much more frequently in the past, you would usually only have a short amount of time to present your study, and more often than not, hardly enough time is available at the end of your talk for questions or meaningful discussions with the audience. During the meeting&amp;rsquo;s plenary discussion, one of the main suggestions for future meetings was to have more poster presentations and less oral presentations, of which I am delighted about and of which I think should be the better way moving forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were also some insightful and interesting talks during the oral keynote presentation sessions. Of note were talks by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thuy Le Toan (CESBIO, France) who presented about the BIOMASS Mission, the first ever P-band SAR sensor planned to be launched in space by 2022 to observe tropical forests. The BIOMASS mission is a truly exciting project because it will allow scientists to answer what the role of forests are in the global carbon cycle, and this time with less uncertainty in measurements by utilising SAR tomography; and&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jeffrey Fox (East-West Center, USA) who talked about his long-term research on the expansion of rubber (Hevea brasiliensis) and its implications for water, carbon, and livelihoods across montane mainland Southeast Asia. After his talk, it got me into thinking: with rubber prices currently really low, what would happen to existing rubber plantations? Would these rubber plantations be converted into other plantations with more lucrative agricultural commodities (like oil palm) so that the plantation owners/farmers can profit from their investments? If not, would it potentially open new frontier areas of deforestation to make way for other lucrative plantations that would then serve as an alternative source of income while at the same time keeping their rubber plantations (in wait until prices become more profitable again)?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, it was a pleasure meeting other remote sensing and land change scientists and learning about their research work in the region and elsewhere. Some of them I&amp;rsquo;ve met for the first time (like Xiaobo, Haemi, Prakhar, Garrett), and some who I met in the last science meeting (like Hoa, Arai, Sumalika), and then Thuy whom I&amp;rsquo;ve known before during the ALOS K&amp;amp;C science meetings in Japan as well as Jeff who came to visit our lab in Singapore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./image_02.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Integrating analytical frameworks to investigate land-cover regime shifts in dynamic landscapes</title>
      <link>/publication/2019-sustainability/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/2019-sustainability/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;medium-donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.3390/su11041139&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MOTIVATE Learning.</title>
      <link>/post/2018/08-03-motivate-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Aug 2018 14:16:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2018/08-03-motivate-learning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am stoked to be one of the invited lecturers/visiting experts for next week&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://sc.isprs.org/events/motivate.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;MOTIVATE Learning&lt;/a&gt; activity, a collaborative project organised by the International Society for Photogrammetry and Remote Sensing Student Consortium (&lt;a href=&#34;http://sc.isprs.org/home.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;ISPRS SC&lt;/a&gt;), the Geoinformatics and Space Technology Development Agency (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gistda.or.th/main/en&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;GISTDA&lt;/a&gt;) of Thailand, and the ASEAN Research and Training Center for Space Technology and Applications (&lt;a href=&#34;http://artsa.gistda.or.th/about/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;ARTSA&lt;/a&gt;), which will be held at the Space Krenovation Park in Chonburi, Thailand. MOTIVATE Learning aims to build the capacity of students and young professionals in the fields of remote sensing, photogrammetry, and spatial information sciences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will be participating in next week&amp;rsquo;s activity, the ISPRS Summer School and Hackathon, which intends to train participants with state-of-the-art geospatial technology through a week-long, fun-filled geekfest consisting of lectures, practical break-out sessions, and hackathon. Specifically, I will be delivering a series of presentations and hands-on exercises about &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;A Synergistic Approach on Mapping using Remote Sensing and GIS&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, of which the official brief topic description is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the evolution of technology, different kinds of satellite imageries are now being collected by various satellite missions. In the past, data scarcity used to be one of the major challenges, but in the present, the era of big data has arrived. How do we make use of different satellite imageries and is it possible to develop a robust synergistic approach on mapping using remote sensing and GIS? This topic aims to explore which satellite imageries can be used in addressing scientific and societal issues and to develop a potential methodology on how to improve results through a synergistic mapping approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence, this will give me the opportunity to talk about my on-going research on understanding land-system change dynamics in Myanmar, specifically my recent &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.3390/rs10020306&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Remote Sensing paper&lt;/a&gt; on combining optical and radar data for land cover classification and change detection; and then, demonstrate a flavor of &lt;a href=&#34;https://earthengine.google.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Google Earth Engine&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s many applications, particularly to land-system change studies (which then gives me a good platform to share my research on a newly-developed protocol for investigating land-system regime shifts); plus a bit about the research projects I have done over the years under the ALOS Kyoto &amp;amp; Carbon Initiative with my former teammates at Fauna &amp;amp; Flora International, mainly on the synergistic use of optical and radar data for land cover (and mangrove) mapping and monitoring in the Philippines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watch this space for more updates on next week&amp;rsquo;s Summer School activity.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Combined Landsat and L-Band SAR data improves land cover classification and change detection in dynamic tropical landscapes</title>
      <link>/publication/2018-remote-sens/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/2018-remote-sens/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;medium-donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.3390/rs10020306&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spatial relationships between above-ground biomass and bird species biodiversity in Palawan, Philippines</title>
      <link>/publication/2017-plos-one/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/2017-plos-one/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;medium-donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.1371/journal.pone.0186742&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Political transition and emergent forest‐conservation issues in Myanmar</title>
      <link>/publication/2017-conserv-biol-horizon-scan/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/2017-conserv-biol-horizon-scan/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;medium-donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.1111/cobi.13021&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Designing maps for the color vision impaired.</title>
      <link>/post/2017/09-16-designing-maps-color-vision-impaired/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Sep 2017 20:51:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2017/09-16-designing-maps-color-vision-impaired/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Cartography involves the drawing of maps, which in fact is both a science and an art. I&amp;rsquo;ve come to learn in the course of my years of study and professional experience that mapmaking is not as easy as it seems. Maps tell a story. And for maps to effectively tell that story, the mapmaker should think not only about the main subject of the map, but should also give due consideration to the various map elements such as their position and balance across the map, as well as the accuracy of the measurements, and the styling of these elements which involve, for example, the choice of colors, line weights, among other considerations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be honest, although I&amp;rsquo;ve been making maps for my entire professional career, I have never considered color vision impairment in the design of maps, at least those that I have made myself. (For instance, the green and red color scheme that I consistently use to depict forest loss and forest gain would be the same shade of gray for a person with color vision impairment.) I have always kept in mind the psychology of colors in maps to help get the message across to the users of these maps, thereby allowing them to better understand the story that the map intends to tell. But unfortunately, I have not put myself in the shoes of a person with color blindness and have given enough thought on how they would perceive and understand those maps. At least not yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The opportunity to rectify this finally came in the process of finalising a map figure for the final proof of our recently accepted paper for publication. A colleague of mine, G, suggested that we consider designing the color scheme of the figure to be more friendly for color blind people. It was a brilliant suggestion. I had not thought of it at first (yet again) and I welcomed it because it gave me the chance to learn and design maps for both people with normal vision and color vision impairments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To implement this, luckily an app called &lt;a href=&#34;http://colororacle.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Color Oracle&lt;/a&gt; existed, which is a free color blindness simulator that can be used across computer platforms. It shows what people with common color vision impairments would see in real time, thus allowing a person to select appropriate colors in designing the color scheme of a material, website, or publication. Color Oracle basically applies a color filter over the full screen of your computer regardless of the software in use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, the screenshots of the same portion of the map figure below was the result of the Color Oracle app showing me what a person with normal vision would see and what a color vision impaired person would see. Through these color filters, I then selected colors that would ensure the images can be read by people with normal vision and color blindness. It adds another layer of consideration in designing maps, even making it more challenging, but this ensures that the map can be read by and be accessible to the widest possible audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./image_01.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; /&gt;&lt;em&gt;Screenshots of the same portion of a map figure showing the colors that people with normal color vision would see (leftmost image) and the colors that people with color vision impairments would see, particularly those with deuteranopia (2nd from left), protanopia (3rd from left), and tritanopia (rightmost image).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For additional reading, visit the &lt;a href=&#34;http://colororacle.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Color Oracle&lt;/a&gt; website and read the papers by Jenny &amp;amp; Kelso (2007a, 2007b) to learn more about the design of information graphics and maps that are accessible for color-impaired readers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jenny, B., Kelso, N. V. (2007a). Designing maps for the color-vision impaired. &lt;em&gt;Bulletin of the Society of Cartographers&lt;/em&gt; SoC, &lt;strong&gt;41&lt;/strong&gt;, 9-12. [&lt;a href=&#34;http://colororacle.org/resources/2007_JennyKelso_DesigningMapsForTheColourVisionImpaired.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jenny, B., Kelso, N. V. (2007b). Color design for the color vision impaired. &lt;em&gt;Cartographic Perspectives&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;58&lt;/strong&gt;, 61-67. [&lt;a href=&#34;http://colororacle.org/resources/2007_JennyKelso_ColorDesign_lores.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Untangling the proximate causes and underlying drivers of deforestation and forest degradation in Myanmar</title>
      <link>/publication/2017-conserv-biol-causal-network/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/2017-conserv-biol-causal-network/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;medium-donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.1111/cobi.12984&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using spatial analysis to explore synergies between the Aichi Biodiversity Targets and REDD&#43; in the Philippines—a preliminary analysis</title>
      <link>/publication/2014-unep-wcmc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/2014-unep-wcmc/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
