<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>R | Jose Don De Alban</title>
    <link>/tags/r/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tags/r/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>R</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2020 Jose Don De Alban</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 02 Feb 2020 15:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/don_baybayin.png</url>
      <title>R</title>
      <link>/tags/r/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rebuilding my new website with Hugo, R blogdown, GitHub, and Netlify.</title>
      <link>/post/2020/02-02-building-my-new-website-with-hugo-blogdown-netlify/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Feb 2020 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2020/02-02-building-my-new-website-with-hugo-blogdown-netlify/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have been rebuilding my personal website using a static site generator, first, because I wanted a cleaner and streamlined site with an easy upkeep, plus I was motivated to learn the new tools, and more importantly, to move away from hosting on Wordpress due to the really annoying ads. The process was on and off, and although I found tips online that you can indeed complete it in a day or less, I only found time to on it very intermittently, mostly while in transit at airport terminals and during flights and over weekends, which was why it took about three months to deploy the site—and only last night, finally! The website is still incomplete and still under reconstruction, with most of my old blog posts and pages from my old 14n121e website to be slowly incorporated in my new website slowly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below, I have put together some guidance on how I built my new website, which you may find helpful in case you were wondering how you could go about building one for yourself too. I tried to put together the major steps with as much detail as I can recall, albeit I may have missed minor ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prerequisites&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After some prior searching online, I settled on using Hugo, R blogdown, GitHub, and Netlify as the combination of tools/resources I would employ for setting up and rebuilding my website. Note that I did not mind reconstructing the site manually (e.g., migrating contents such as blog post one by one) because it was not alot and also so I could understand the inner workings, hence I did not pursue (semi-)automated ways that existed for migrating content from Wordpress to the new site. To get started, I ensured the following online accounts were set up and the software tools were installed in my Mac OSX machine:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://git-scm.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Git&lt;/a&gt; and a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; account as the version control system for tracking the changes in a dedicated repository containing the website contents;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;R&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://rstudio.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;RStudio&lt;/a&gt;, the premier IDE for R, plus the &lt;a href=&#34;https://bookdown.org/yihui/blogdown/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;blogdown&lt;/a&gt; R package developed by &lt;a href=&#34;https://yihui.org/en/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Yihue Xie&lt;/a&gt;;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Then, &lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt;, an open-source static site generator for building websites, plus the &lt;a href=&#34;https://themes.gohugo.io/academic/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Academic&lt;/a&gt; Hugo theme by &lt;a href=&#34;https://georgecushen.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;George Cushen&lt;/a&gt;, of which was my personal choice as the theme for creating a simple and customisable website using the &lt;a href=&#34;https://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Markdown&lt;/a&gt; markup language (and it is apt for academics/scientists/researchers);&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition, I used some advanced features including &lt;a href=&#34;https://disqus.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Disqus&lt;/a&gt; to enable comments and discussions, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://marketingplatform.google.com/about/analytics/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Google Analytics&lt;/a&gt; to understand my website traffic; and&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finally, a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.netlify.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Netlify&lt;/a&gt; account to enable a fast and continuous deployment of the website, once the GitHub repository was connected and the build settings were added.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For most of the above, I already had prexisting registered accounts and had installed the tools, except for Netlify (so I had to sign up for a new account) and R blogdown and Hugo (both of which I had to newly install).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Creating a repository on Github&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Installing blogdown, Hugo and the Academic theme&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a final note, I have to say that the initial setup required some effort and time to learn a few new tools—and troubleshoot as required—but in the end, I was satisfied with the process and the outcome, and also from knowing that from here on the upkeep required to maintain my online presence would be minimal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used several resources online including&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;instructions of how to use Hugo, blogdown, and Netlify&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;helpful and easy-to-follow instructions form
Yihue Xie for blogdown
George Cushen for the Academic theme for Hugo&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;plus blog posts by XXX&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Katie Scanton&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Erika Fille Legara
Zhi Yang&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I referred to their posts, and sometimes even the GitHub-hosted repositories hosting their sites, as well as finding many bits of inspiration from the bespoke designs of their own websites&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;was really helpful&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Special thanks to Lloyd Zapanta for developing a true type font for the Baybayin script, which is the indigenous alphabet writing script of pre-colonial Philippines. He designed several true type fonts of the Baybayin script, of which I particularly used Baybayin Sisil rendition for creating my website logo, which is essentially my name written with Baybayin characters.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Repos on GitHub.</title>
      <link>/post/2019/08-11-repos-on-github/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Aug 2019 20:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2019/08-11-repos-on-github/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have been sharing the coding materials and resources related to my research on my &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/dondealban&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;GitHub page&lt;/a&gt; but I have not had the chance to blog about these here at all, even briefly. And so, let me make this short introduction on my activities on GitHub, which does seem to show (and share) more of my research activity than in this blog. It&amp;rsquo;s just been about time too that I updated the &amp;lsquo;mugshot&amp;rsquo; on my GitHub page, which used to show an old (younger) photo of me, and now, more appropriately, shows a recent photo of me taken during the wedding of a dear colleague. Anyway&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./image_01.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, the repositories that accompany some of my published papers, either those I have led or had the great opportunity to co-author. I put together these materials to supplement the published papers, thereby creating a backup of the materials used and developed through the study such as data, results, scripts, and figures. By doing this, I was aiming to encourage not just other scientists and researchers but also my future self to do better science by fostering research reproducibility and transparency. It also improves the overall impact of my own research. Some of these repositories include materials for my &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/dondealban/ms-remote-sens-2018&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;2018 Remote Sensing&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/dondealban/ms-sustainability-2019&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;2019 Sustainability&lt;/a&gt; papers, as well as a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/dondealban/ms-conserv-biol-2017&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;2017 Conservation Biology&lt;/a&gt; paper, all of which were done together with my lab members and principal investigator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./image_02.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, I&amp;rsquo;ve created some repositories over the last couple of years for a lecture I gave at the ISPRS Student Consortium Summer School and Hackathon in 2018 where I shared about my land change research and ran a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/dondealban/isprs-sc-summer-school&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;crash course on Google Earth Engine&lt;/a&gt;, and a short &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/dondealban/tutorial-qgis-maxent&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;tutorial on species distribution modeling using MaxEnt and R&lt;/a&gt; that I did for my labmates during a lab retreat in 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I&amp;rsquo;ve also developed a couple of long how-to guides or tutorials while I was starting to learn some R packages in pursuit of my research ideas. There was one on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/dondealban/learning-stm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;stm package&lt;/a&gt; on structural topic modeling for text data mining and automated content analysis; and the other on the &lt;a href=&#34;(https://github.com/dondealban/learning-intensity-analysis)&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;intensity analysis package&lt;/a&gt;, which has been a key component of my research on land use/cover change analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quite frankly, I am stoked to see that users on GitHub have found these repositories (and some others I have not mentioned) useful as indicated by the number of stars or forks (take the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/dondealban/learning-stm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;learning-stm&lt;/a&gt; repo, for example).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please do watch my GitHub space for more updates on my research activities. If you find the materials and resources in any way helfpful, please &amp;lsquo;star&amp;rsquo; the repository page on GitHub, or cite the papers or accompanying repositories if you used them for your research. In case you want to contribute to the content in any of the repositories, please feel free to fork the repo and submit your pull request.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./image_03.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./image_04.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./image_05.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
