<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>agricultural expansion | Jose Don De Alban</title>
    <link>/tags/agricultural-expansion/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tags/agricultural-expansion/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>agricultural expansion</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2020 Jose Don De Alban</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/don_baybayin.png</url>
      <title>agricultural expansion</title>
      <link>/tags/agricultural-expansion/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reconciling Agricultural Expansion and Forest Conservation in Myanmar.</title>
      <link>/project/04_myanmar-tier2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/04_myanmar-tier2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RECONCILING AGRICULTURAL EXPANSION AND FOREST CONSERVATION IN THE NEW MYANMAR (2016-2019).&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Myanmar’s rapid socio-economic transition presents a unique opportunity to study the influence of economic development on biodiversity conservation in the context of governance transformation. The overarching objective of this project is to understand and evaluate the drivers of land use change and deforestation in Myanmar, and to increase the resilience of protected areas to protect biodiversity in the face of rapid new pressures imposed by increased foreign direct investment. This project intends to combine local case studies, geospatial modelling tools, and policy analyses to inform the fluid policy context of Myanmar and generate novel insights for long-term conservation and management of biodiversity by improving land use planning, protected area management, and improving policy tools for environmental safeguarding. A spatially-explicit, hierarchical approach to this problem is pursued through the following three inter-related objectives:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Broad, country-wide analysis to evaluate land-use change scenarios based on present and future agricultural productivity, commodity prices and forest rents.&lt;/strong&gt; This objective is done by generating top-down, macro-economic land rent models that utilize national and global-level data and creating scenarios based on expected future economic opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Local, case-study analysis to understand how individual actors might behave when given new agricultural opportunities associated with increased investment.&lt;/strong&gt; This objective is achieved by developing bottom-up agent-based models integrating local perception data, to predict areas most vulnerable to deforestation and land use change surrounding a subset of priority protected areas.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Develop policy recommendations that reconcile increased international investment, new opportunities for livelihood improvement through agricultural expansion and intensification, with biodiversity conservation in Myanmar.&lt;/strong&gt; This objective includes the conduct of scenario analyses of the models constructed for 1) and 2) above, based on present conditions and potential policy options. This should lead to science-based policy recommendations related to infrastructure investment, agricultural expansion, protected area conservation and environmental safeguards based on realistic scenarios going forward.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Conceptualising and Articulating the Drivers of Deforestation in Myanmar.</title>
      <link>/project/03_myanmar-tier1/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/03_myanmar-tier1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CONCEPTUALISING AND ARTICULATING THE DRIVERS OF DEFORESTATION IN THE NEW MYANMAR (2015–2018).&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project intends to develop a conceptual framework for Myanmar that distinguishes and identifies the various stakeholders, resources, and their relationships set within the dynamic policy landscape. Moreover, the project intends to develop a holistic, multi-disciplinary perspective on the emerging trends in Myanmar that are likely to have an impact on the forest-agriculture interface. The two specific objectives of the project are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To develop a qualitative conceptual framework that identifies, describes, and links key
stakeholders that influence forest conservation, agriculture, and natural resource extraction in Myanmar, and embeds those relationships within a socio-economic and policy context. The framework should describe the stakeholders, agents, and contextual factors that will later inform scenario analysis for a spatially-explicit, top-down, rent-based agriculture-forest model.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To conduct a horizon scan that identifies the highest priority threats and opportunities that Myanmar’s increased international engagement will have for forest conservation. This will lead to novel, interdisciplinary insights on how Myanmar’s new international engagement may lead to new physical outcomes, such as agricultural intensification, deforestation, or agroindustrial expansion.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
